Finding Aid for Barbara Hays-Hamilton Papers 1975-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Barbara Hays-Hamilton Papers 1975-1986
Hays-Hamilton, Barbara.
9777 Aa 2
Feminist and Equal Rights Amendment activist from Midland, Michigan, officer of Michigan National Organization of Women; papers document her work on women's issues in NOW, in various political campaigns and as a lobbyist.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Barbara Hays-Hamilton (donor no. 8572) in March, 1997.
This collection is open to research.
Barbara Hays-Hamilton, a staunch feminist and supporter of the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), joined the Midland chapter of the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women (NOW) in 1975. She served as president of the Midland chapter in 1978. She then held several positions within the Michigan Conference of NOW. These included positions such as chair of the ERA and the lesbian rights task forces and administrative vice president. Hays-Hamilton was elected to two one-year terms as president of the Michigan Conference of NOW beginning in 1984. During her term as president, the Conference actively supported Mondale/Ferraro in the 1984 elections. The Michigan Conference of NOW was also very active in state politics and lobbying efforts. Issues such as abortion rights and comparable worth legislation were prominent concerns. As president, Hays-Hamilton represented the Michigan Conference of NOW to other levels of NOW as well as to other activist groups. These other groups included the Michigan Women's Assembly, a coalition of women's group from throughout the state.
Ms. Hays-Hamilton also helped to form the Midland chapter of ERAmerica. In 1986, she received a degree in political science from Central Michigan University. After completing her degree she took a position at the national office of NOW in Washington, D.C.
This collection contains five series:
Campaigns and Elections
Legislative Activities
Michigan Women's Assembly
National Organization for Women (NOW)
Topical Files
The Barbara Hays-Hamiton papers document her activities as member and officer of the Michigan Chapter of the National Organization for Women and the Michigan Women's Assembly, her participation in political campaigns and legislative work on behalf of women's issues and other feminist activities and causes.
Subject:
Hays-Hamilton, Barbara.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Michigan Women's Assembly.; National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.; Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; Feminists--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Hays-Hamilton, Barbara.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Campaigns and Elections
  Campaigns and Elections (1976-1986, .3 linear feet) contains information regarding the Michigan Conference of NOW's support of candidates for office. Much of this materials details Hays-Hamilton's activities as president of the Michigan Conference of NOW and its political action committee. There is, however, material from other organizations such as Women against Reagan. The bulk of this material concerns the 1984 elections and in particular the presidential election.
  - Elections 1976 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Election 1984
    - Michigan NOW materials 1984 (Box 1)
    - Mondale Campaign 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - National NOW materials 1984 (Box 1)
    - Women Against Reagan 1984 (Box 1)
  - Congress
    - 3rd District, Howard Wolpe 1984 (Box 1)
    - 4th District, Charles Rodebaugh 1984 (Box 1)
    - 5th District, Gary McInerney 1984 (Box 1)
    - 6th District, Bob Carr 1984 (Box 1)
    - 9th District, John Senger 1984 (Box 1)
    - 10th District, Don Albosta 1976-1984 (Box 1)
    - Levin Senate Campaign 1984 (Box 1)
  - Direct Mail Appeals 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - HumanServe Fund 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Michigan NOW PAC
    - Board 1981-1986 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, undated (Box 1)
    - Endorsements 1982-1985 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1984 (Box 1)
- Legislative Activities
  Legislative Activities (1977-1986, .3 linear feet) describes the efforts of Hays-Hamilton and the Michigan Conference of NOW to get women's issues addressed by lawmaking bodies. The struggle to have the Equal Rights Amendment adopted is prominent in this series. There is also information about Hays-Hamilton's opposition to the calling of a national constitutional convention as well as information about several initiatives being considered by the state legislature.
  - Affirmative Action 1985 (Box 1)
  - "Capitol: Woman" Newsletter 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights Acts 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Comparable Worth 1985 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Convention 1984 (Box 1)
  - Equal Rights Amendment (ERA)
    - Midland ERAmerica 1972-1982 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Friend of the Court Child Support Guidelines (Proposed) 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Immigration Reform 1984 (Box 1)
  - Job Training Partnership Act (JTPA) 1985 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Citizens to Protect the Constitution 1984 (Box 1)
  - Michigan NOW Legislative Materials 1977-1986 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Woman's Commission 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Uniform Marital Property Act (UMPA) circa 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Welfare 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- Michigan Women's Assembly
  The Michigan Women's Assembly (1975-1986, .3 linear feet) is a political coalition of women's groups from across the state. The Michigan Conference of NOW was one these groups. The assembly adopted platforms in 1982, 1984 and 1986 to bring attention to women's issues. As president of the Michigan Conference of NOW, Hays-Hamilton participated in some of the leadership activities of the assembly such as a retreat for the leadership to plan strategy.
  - Board of Directors 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Comparable Worth 1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1975-1986 (Box 1)
  - Platform 1982-1986, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Retreat 1984-1985 (Box 1)
- National Organization for Women (NOW)
  The National Organization for Women (NOW) (1977-1986, .9 linear feet) series documents Hays-Hamilton's involvement with NOW at the local (Midland), state (Michigan), regional (Great Lakes) and national levels. Examples of the type of material found in this series are bylaws, minutes and correspondence. The majority of the series relates to the activities of the Michigan Conference of NOW when she was president. The Michigan Conference of NOW maintained no state office so each officer kept her own records. The researcher is directed to the records of the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women (call no. 85326 Bj 2) and the papers of Monica Smiley (call no. 85377 Aa 2) and Marian McCracken (call no. 9643 Aa 2) for more information on the Michigan Conference of NOW.
  - Great Lakes Region (Box 1)
    - Bylaws undated (Box 1)
    - Conferences
      - 1978 (Box 1)
      - 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1986 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1983-1986 (Box 1)
    - Minutes 1984 (Box 1)
  - Michigan (Box 2)
    - Bylaws and Policies 1977-1986 (Box 2)
    - Conferences 1980-1986, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1983-1986 (Box 2)
    - Legislative Liaison 1978-1986 (Box 2)
    - Membership 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - "Michigan NOW Times Newsletter," 1978-1986 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous circa 1977-1985 (Box 2)
    - Officers Meetings 1981-1986, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - State Coordinating Council 1981-1986, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Treasurer 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Midland
    - History circa 1982 (Box 2)
    - Notes and Correspondence 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - National
    - Board (Box 2)
    - Bylaws and Guidelines 1977-1983 (Box 2)
    - Chapter Development 1981-1985 (Box 2)
    - Conferences 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1983-1986 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1985-1986 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (1981-1986, .2 linear feet) contains information about a number of issues of concern to Hays-Hamilton. These include abortion rights, lesbian/gay rights, and minority rights/racism.
  - Abortion Rights 1982-1986 (Box 2)
  - Lesbian/Gay Rights 1981-1985 (Box 2)
  - Minority Women Committee/Racism 1985 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Organization for Human Rights (MOHR) 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Older Women's League 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Photographs 1984-1986 (Box 2)